You've probably heard
about the
August
payrolls report, but what's far more
important is what
you didn't hear, or
what didn't actually
happen.  Namely, the
market reaction.  By
market, we
mean interest
rates, bonds,
fixed income instruments,
not necessarily the
stock market or
financial media.  There
was a time when the date of the
payroll report was circled on the
calendar.  “
Payday Friday” was a
reliable ritual.
Now, given
how the data is coming out and
how the views have significantly
influenced it
over the past few
years,
salary reporting has been
seriously undervalued, and for
good reason, as we'll
see in this
video.  So, again:
everyone heard the magic
wage numbers, that
staggering number
that we'll talk about
, but much more
important was the
lack of reaction
in the market, especially
now when everyone
is talking about the "
hawkish" policy of
central banks and
the Fed meeting in a
couple of weeks.  Will
they raise
rates?  Will
salary figures influence
politicians' opinions?  As
for the
bond market, this was a
minor event,
consistent with
much other
data, as we
will see below.  Steve,
I mean, that
was your main
takeaway on "
payday Friday,"
because you're a veteran of
money management
and macroeconomic
analysis, and "
payday Friday" used to be
everyone.  It was the same
significant event
that we all marked
on the calendar and
looked forward to every
month, the first
Friday of every
month.  It was the
day when you had to
be glued to your
screens at 8:30 in the morning
when the numbers came out,
and today it is becoming
less and less of a
significant event.
Yes, absolutely
Jeff.  This is a market that
, typically, should
be an event that moves the
markets: blockbuster
earnings or a big
disappointment—you
see
stocks and bonds move and
everything starts
to correct, but
boy, it's been
pretty boring, as we've
already seen.  The stock
market didn't really
react, and as we're
going to
discuss, the
bond market says, "
Wait, you can
look at the
headline,
but when we start
looking at the internals of
this
report, it becomes clear
why there was no reaction
."
Yes, I think
part of it is because
we are used to it being
unreliable.
You know, the
payrolls report was considered
the most reliable
indicator of the
labor market, and it could be
argued, as
many have done
for
years, that it was the
most accurate
macroeconomic
indicator in the entire
catalog.  But we've
seen
this over and over again, in fact since late
2023—and this is not
ironic—when the
bond market rally
started to gain
momentum because it
was a market signal of
weakening
employment that wasn't
reflected in the
BLS surveys, because the
BLS methodology is simply
not adapted to
such conditions.  The BLS
actually stated, "We
assume that
the economy is either on the
upswing, it's
expanding, it's, you
know, looking like
any post-war
growth that we've
seen from the 1940s
to 2007, or it's in a
recession."  We have
no
middle ground here.  We will either
record the statistics
on the trend cycle in the
expansion chart,
or we will look for the
next recession.  We do
n't know how
to cope with the fact that we
have forgotten how to grow.
And this environment, where they "
forgot to grow
," has wreaked havoc on
their statistical
adjustments, causing
them to initially
overestimate
employment rates, especially
with the
birth-
death model, and then
have to significantly
revise those numbers
later.  When you
do this
long enough...look,
you'll do it once or
twice, and people will say, "
Okay, maybe there's
a little problem here."    "
It could be something
short-term."
But you do it
month after month, and
not just in 2024 or 2025
, we've seen
significant revisions
even this year.  You
do this for a few
years and people say,
"This number
doesn't mean anything at all,"
which was actually the
market reaction, and in
many ways it's
right.
And Jeff, that's a really
great point,
because if you look at the
last two years,
the number of
jobs has only been marginally
positive, and I'm just
embellishing
it a little bit more by
taking the
average.  There's really
nothing
exciting here.  So, are
we suddenly supposed to
believe that
all these
jobs and these
upward revisions have appeared?  And suddenly,
you know, after what
we've seen in the soft
survey data,
the rise in
energy prices, suddenly
there's this
euphoria, and suddenly
businesses are going to
go out and
hire people en masse before the
fall season?  The data
does not confirm what
we are actually
seeing in the real
economy with
consumer spending
.  And that's one of the main
reasons why we've
seen absolutely
no reaction, because
the market is saying, "Hey, like
you said, you fooled
us once, hahaha."
Okay, you fooled us
twice, but hey,
we won't be fooled this time
."  We know what your
game is, and we know
the numbers aren't real.
Yes, we've seen that before.
This is not once or twice,
you know, I just
did a detailed
analysis for our
Euro Dollar
University subscribers.  We went
through the numbers.  You can
look
back a couple of years.    Let
's go back to 2024.
May 2024, the
employment figure
initially came in at
272,000. Under very
similar circumstances:
rising
oil prices, the Federal
Reserve
is talking about a strong,
resilient economy and
high inflation, and that it
may
have to
raise rates again,
or at least
keep them
high for longer.
And those 272 today?  78.
What would the
market reaction have been if they had
initially announced
78,000?  Instead, there were 272
.  The following month, in
June, the starting
figure was 206.
Today?  87. The
next month,
July, 114—began
to cause
concern.
Today, it is believed that it
was 53. August, if
you remember, August 2024
, just before
the Fed lowered its
key rate by 50
basis points.    The
jobs report
came out and things
seemed a little
better, as if the
labor market had stabilized
after the
Japanese "carry trade
" exploded, and people
were talking about the risk of a
recession in the US, which, by
the way, happened.  The
August employment report came out in
early September 2024
with a figure of 142,000. Not
great, but
notice
how similar that is to
what we just
talked about.  Similar
circumstances.  142,000 people
who said the
labor market situation was stabilizing
.  Guess what
number it is today?
Nine.  Not 142,
actually zero.  It's
only 2024.  We see
numerous examples in
2025.  April 2025
, in the midst of a tariff
explosion and tariff
fury.  The
employment reports come out
in early May 2025
, 177,000. Today
it's 108. The
employment reports for
May 2025
came out in early
June of last year,
139,000. Today they say it
was 13. So, yes,
we've seen this movie
over and over again.  The employment report
comes out with a big
number.  Maybe
even
some views are added, and
then everything
goes back to the same
trend.  This is an
important point—a
trend, and it is on it that
the market is focused,
not on a fleeting
monthly report, which
, even if
reviewed, is the fruit of
everyone's imaginary statistics.
Before we
continue with our
video today,
let me ask
you a question.  What
if your gold
could actually
pay you
even more gold every month?
This is what
today's video sponsor
, Monetary Metals, allows you to do.  Here's how it
works.  You still
own
the gold, it's
registered in your name,
fully
insured, but
instead of
just lying around doing nothing
, it starts
working for you.
Monetary Metals has created a
system that
turns inactive
gold into
productive gold,
generating real
income in physical
gold, not dollars
.  No sales,
trades, or
conversions.  You
keep your
gold, and you
get
more of it every month.  It's a simple
idea, but it
solves a big
problem.  If gold
is money, it should
behave like money.
And now it's finally
possible.  If you are a
long-term
gold owner
looking for a smarter
way to store
value, visit
monetary-metals.com/snyder.  Once again
, this is monetary-metals.com/snyder.  I
highly
recommend booking
a call with them
today to
see if
they are a good fit for you.
We thank Monetary Metals
for their sponsorship, and
now let's get back to the
rest of our video.
And you know what
trends I'm talking about?
Probably the
most important trend
I'm looking at here
is
average hourly
earnings, because if you
suddenly see
stable
employment figures and then a
spike, what would you
look for first
?  This is when
employers say, "
Hey, wait a minute."  I
need you to
stay."  And so,
how do they do it?
They are starting to
raise
average hourly
earnings.
We've
seen virtually no
change in the last 2 months, especially in the
subgroup of production
and non-management
workers that
I'm focused on—the
average working
American.  But if
you look at the trend over the
last few years, you
know, if this
was a stock chart, you would
n't buy them.
You know, you wouldn't catch a
falling knife.  So
the idea that we'll
go through the summer with
some mediocre
growth......and then
suddenly see a
big jump in
August hints that
something has changed.  So
why don't we see
this in
average hourly
earnings?  Or why are
n't we seeing a big
jump in the average
number of
hours worked
per week?  It seems like
we saw an increase of
one-tenth, which
again is
practically nothing.  So
if you look at the
fundamentals of the
employment report, you
say, “Wait a
minute.  "Is
this
large figure confirmed?"  And
the market says: “Look
, we can’t be fooled by
your main
number.  You can
show, like,
hey, look at this.
But if we look
deeper, we understand:
all these numbers are just a
figment of our imagination.  They will be
revised downwards
because ordinary
American
workers see no
signs of
improvement.
Yes, last week
we saw other
sources of data regarding the
employment situation.
In particular,
private
payroll reports from
ADP have been released.  They are
slowing down.  This is
not yet a negative
indicator, but it is
barely turning
positive again.  And, more importantly,
we saw the same
pattern that
we observed in
many other
sources: a small
spike during the
energy shock,
which is quite logical.
You know, many
manufacturers
tried to
release products as quickly as possible.
This has spilled over into the
service sector.  In
addition, there was a boost from the
World Cup.
So, we had a
temporary
employment boom that everyone
took as a sign of a
magical
recovery and
labor market strength.  Quite
expectedly, these mini-
cycles that I've been talking about for the
last few years
show a
temporary spike, an
artificial uptick, and
then a decline on
the eve of the fall, which is
quite natural
given the
energy situation
that you mentioned,
Steve.  As does the general
economic trend, which
remains
stagnant.  So,
ADP figures
have already started to decline.
Another study
from the Bureau of
Labor Statistics itself is the
JOLTS survey.
Forget about
vacancies, this is another
unreliable indicator
, but even they,
especially in
terms of
percentage
, do not look
good.  But the
JOLTS hiring index
was the third worst
this entire cycle, which
again proves that no matter what
we think about the
layoffs, which are
only
partially occurring, hiring
remains extremely
low.  This is exactly what
we expected from the
payrolls report
, as it is
supported by
numerous
data sources—both outside and inside
the Bureau of
Labor Statistics,
and across the
entire macroeconomic landscape,
including the market.
Again, the
market reaction was: we
know what
other data says, we know
what the underlying trend is
.  So yes, we got
another temporary
jump in the
payroll report, which will have
no impact on the situation
in the medium
and long
term.
You know, let's
talk about other
data, because we should
look at the
manufacturing sector.    The
ISM report is out, and I
know the numbers are
positive, but
let's face it
, because what do
they indicate?  They
say, "Look, there's
a lot of
inventory accumulating here."  And
the justification for this is
that producers
believe that
inflation will increase.
So if you're constantly
building up inventory
month after month and it's
not moving, what does that
tell you?  Does this
mean that consumers
cannot
afford such prices?  At
some point,
manufacturers will start
to cut back on volume,
which is important because what have we
seen?  Orders
increased a little, but no,
they didn't hire new
employees.  But what
was really interesting,
Jeff, when we
talk about
leading
indicators, and this
brings us back to the
payroll data: why
doesn't the market believe this
headline number?  Has the
backlog of new
orders begun to shrink, which is exactly what
should happen during an
economic slowdown, because if
orders were growing
along with
production and
prices, as well as
other indicators,
what would that
indicate?  That
the economy is strong,
consumers are active and
spending money.  But
it is shrinking.
Manufacturers know this and
see it
happening in
real time,
saying, "Wait
a minute."  "We don't
need to hire, because
if this trend
continues, we'll
have to lay off people
."  Then we move on to the
services sector.  Again
, hey, another
positive number
over 50. But what
happened?  In the
employment subsector, we see a
reduction.  Of course,
not significant.  This does not
indicate mass
layoffs, but
perhaps
working hours are being reduced a little somewhere
.
Some
part-time jobs may be disappearing
.  Still, nothing
serious, but still a
slight
reduction.  This is
strong evidence
that these official salary figures
could just as easily have been
made up, because that's what the
market sees.
That's the thing, isn't it
, Steve?  Employers
don't seem to believe in this
growth, and
rightly so.
I mean, they
understand that their
profits are being squeezed
.  Yes, profitability is
still relatively
high in a historical
context, but when
you are being hit on margins from
all sides, plus you
see weakness in
consumer spending, which,
by the way, is constantly
being confirmed by
new signs.  I
looked at the reports of the
Circle K store chain
to see what
they say about
consumers, particularly
about fuel.  Consumers
were buying, you know,
Circle K's revenue from
gasoline sales was up
33% year over year
.
Huge, simply
huge nominal
growth in
gasoline sales.  Volumes fell
by 1%.  Think about what
this means for the
average
consumer.
The average
consumer paid a
third more to
get 1% less.
This is the true
definition of impoverishment
.  So, a business knows
its customers.  They
know what's
happening in
the macroeconomics,
regardless of all the
hype in the financial
media or the stock
market, they know the
real state of affairs.
They understand the
current conditions and do not
believe in this
economic upswing
, at least not in
optimistic sentiment
and some other
indicators.  They
say, “Okay, if
we have some
upfront demand,
inventory build-up,
some service providers
regrouping, we
know this won’t
last long.  "So
we will
deal with
current
orders as much as possible, and then
we will not hire
a bunch of employees who
, in our opinion, we will not
need until
the fall and the end of this
year."  So, there
was no hiring growth anywhere except for this
one month in the
payroll report.
Even in the
household survey report.    The
household survey
did show a
recovery in
August, according to the
latest data
just released,
but it came after a
dismal 6-month
period.  And, by the way, this is
how
household surveys work.
It usually
fluctuates up and
down.  It's part of his
nature.  So the fact that the
household survey
rebounded after
two very bad
months in a row and a 6-
month decline also
tells us nothing.  Again
, the trend is important,
and the data and
market reaction suggest that the
trend remains
unchanged, and there is every
reason to doubt the
payroll report
because we have seen it
too many times
before.
You know, Jeff, let's
talk about
why we're unlikely to
see any further
growth in
employment rates.  And you know,
if you look back at the
last couple of years,
what was the main
problem in the business?
They were squeezed in the
margins.  You know, in terms of
profits, they were barely
making ends meet
, and then
suddenly the situation
changed because of
rising prices, and the
profit margin
started to expand
.  So the idea that
they're going to rush out and
hire a bunch of people and
say, "Hey, you know
what?  The heyday
has returned."  Do
n't even hope.  They
will be boosting
their profits
because many of them are
literally, well,
maybe
months away from
closing if we're
talking about small
businesses;  and they're not in
a position to say, "Hey,
we'll make a little
bet that the rest of the
year will be just
great."  Let's
hire a bunch of people.  "Do
n't even
hope."  So,
think about it from a
business perspective:
they need to see
margin growth, and that's
one of those big
indicators that if
they don't stay
high in the
second half of the year,
they're going to have to
cut costs
because they finally
see, "Oh, finally there's money in the
bank
."  "
I finally have
room to maneuver,
and I don't want that to
change."
Yes, that's also a valid
comment.  We
talked about the K-
shaped economy
among consumers.
Of course, the K-shaped
economy also exists
among businesses.  There are
large corporations that
, well, they're doing
well.  Nobody
complains about big
companies.  Yes,
they may be putting a little
pressure on margins, but
their profitability is
still relatively
high.  And there are small and
medium-sized businesses that
you never
hear about because their stocks are
not traded on the New
York Stock Exchange or
anywhere abroad.    They are the ones
having
problems, and that's why
you don't see mass
waves of layoffs.
They don't have any extra
employees who
can simply
be fired tomorrow
if they have to.  They are already
working with
minimal resources.
So what does this
small and medium
business do?  They
stopped hiring a
few years ago, which
is one of the reasons
why no one is
hiring anyone.  No one is
hiring because small and
medium-sized businesses are not
making enough money
to justify
adding staff.  And,
by the way, too few
new orders are
coming in.  This is a large
part of the economy
that has "forgotten how
to grow" because incomes are
not increasing.  In
some sectors, they are
nominally growing
, but overall there is
simply not enough work for
anyone, which brings us back
to what
Steve was talking about earlier—
hours worked
.  The number of hours is not
increasing much because
there is no real
physical volume of
work for either
producers of goods
or
service providers.  So why would they
hire additional
workers?  And with the
added pressure on the
edge, they think, “I
definitely won’t
hire anyone.  The ones I have that
I really
can't fire,
I'm going to have to
cut their hours a little bit,
" which is what we
continue to see in the
full-time and
part-time employment figures
, as well as in the
hours-of-work data from the
business survey that
Steve referenced.  The
labor market continues to
feel pressure.    It's
just that nobody
sees it, or at least
nobody outside of the
bond market, because
every now and then
these payroll reports come out that
just
blow everyone away.  And no
one realizes, first of all
, that this is a
business as usual for the last few
years, and that these numbers are being
revised significantly
downward over the
coming months, and
maybe even years
, and you don't hear about it
— I mean,
remember that report about
270 thousand new
jobs in
2024.  Do you think
anyone who
was there in early
June 2024
remembers or even
knows that those 272,000 have
now turned
into less than 100?  They
were simply amazed by
those 272 thousand.  They
heard this, along with the rest of
the noise in the mainstream
media, and said, "Yes
, inflation is stable, the Fed will
not cut
rates."  But look
, in the end the Fed does
lower rates.
But that's exactly what the
market wants, isn't it?  He
wants these big numbers
to support
risky operations.
Hey, look, we
need to
keep playing the bearish
bond market.  See, we
told you that rates would
go up and you
should keep
buying stocks because
look at how
great the
payroll reports are.  This will lead
to even more
inflation, more
growth, and, you know,
all of this just
reinforces that
idea.  And so, as you
said, Jeff, why
do they do these
reviews?  Because
after a couple of months or a
year, no one
cares anymore, no one
really remembers it
.  That's not the point.    The
point is to
make the market grow and
convince people
that everything is okay.
Yeah, that's their...that's
their funny
marketing ploy on
Wall Street: "Hey, don't
worry about anything.
Everything is great.  "Everything is
just perfect."
Meanwhile, this
brings us back to the K-
shaped economy.
Ordinary people
can't live like this.  They are
forced to try to
afford at least
something in such an
economy.  And by the way, one more
point here.  This does
n't just apply to
the US.  We have received
further
confirmation of the
mini-boom and
bust cycle in Canada, our
northern neighbors.
They released
employment data
for August, and it's
terrible.  There were several
months in a row when
employment figures
increased.  Again
, this is an artificial
lift, a push from the
premature
accumulation of
activity
associated with the
energy shock.  And
suddenly in August we
see an unexpected
drop of over
40,000 jobs,
with a large number of
full-time positions lost.
Moreover,
labor force participation rates have
fallen again, which is
another
pattern
we see around the
world.  As
the economy weakens and the
labor market begins
to turn around, people don't
just sit on the
sidelines, officially
unemployed,
looking for work.  They
generally give up
because they know that no
one is hiring.  So, in
many ways, this is not
only confirmation of a
mini-cycle recession
in Canada this summer, but also
the same pattern
that we
see
all the time, which
masks hidden
weakness.  Official
unemployment figures
do not actually
reflect the
real level of
unemployment in these
economies.  The USA is a
perfect example.
Hundreds of thousands of
workers have left the
labor market, just
like in Canada.  The scale is
not as large, but it's the
same in Canada.  In
the UK you
see the same
picture.
Participation rates are falling, and everyone
is justifying it with
something, but the bottom line is that
people
are stopping looking for
work.  And the resumption of
the household survey in
August is a perfect
example of this.    The
labor force
shrank
in parallel with the
decline in
employment rates in the
household survey.  So
we get a
one-time increase in
employment in August,
and guess what
happens?  The workforce is
growing.  In other
words, when there is
work, people enter the
labor market.  When there is
no work, they
stop looking and
exit the
labor market.  The official
unemployment rate
does not take them into account, so it
looks much
better in contrast,
which only fuels
the illusion of stability
and resilience, although
in reality, as the
bond market continues to show, this is not the case.
Ultimately, it all
comes down to the fact that
the weakness becomes
impossible to ignore
, we
are back to the “
chip jar” again, and
the Fed starts
cutting rates again.